<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2012s on Misframe</title>
    <link>http://misfra.me/2012/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2012s on Misframe</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; Preetam Jinka</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://misfra.me/2012/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Success, potential, and opportunity.</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/success-potential-and-opportunity</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/success-potential-and-opportunity</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/preetamjinka/7046406061&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/f3bd0bf35f9a505ae13d3f48928ea6ae/tumblr_inline_mfzgk5uoWA1rs73cz.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Capella&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;success:ab772c4809a5deef6f2d9768bca428c5&#34;&gt;Success&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think success is the product of work. Not &lt;em&gt;hard&lt;/em&gt; work, necessarily. Just work. The rest is about two very important things: potential and opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential:ab772c4809a5deef6f2d9768bca428c5&#34;&gt;Potential&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see potential all the time. Academic environments do that. There’s a continuous expansion of human capital. Amazing. For some reason, I think I forgot about my own potential. The past two years of my life have been incredible&amp;mdash;filled with many changes, experiences, and people. I’ve grown, improved, specialized, and built up a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; of potential. Sometimes it just hits me&amp;mdash;“Wow! I did that!” or “I can do this now!” The younger me would look at that and tell me, “That’s great. So what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No one wants to hear about brilliance. They want to see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/preetamjinka/status/141030721467846657&#34;&gt;tweeted&lt;/a&gt; that a little over a year ago. I used to think Twitter was really silly. Why would you use it? A 140-character message would be useless! Well, things changed. Sometimes, 140 characters are enough to serve as a gateway to previous emotions or states of mind. That quote takes me back to what I thought about a year ago. I see the mindset that I had back then. It’s interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is, you can have all the potential in the world but it won’t make a difference until you utilize it. It’s time for me to &lt;em&gt;show&lt;/em&gt; “brilliance.” It’s time for me to execute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;opportunity:ab772c4809a5deef6f2d9768bca428c5&#34;&gt;Opportunity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m in a fantastic position right now. I have an amazing job working for &lt;a href=&#34;http://isomero.us&#34;&gt;Isomerous&lt;/a&gt; with amazing ideas on how to move forward. I have time. I have energy. I have &lt;em&gt;potential&lt;/em&gt;. Now, I have an &lt;em&gt;opportunity&lt;/em&gt;. Everything seems to fit. I’m not religious and I don’t believe in fate. I think the future is a result of what has happened in the past and what occurs in the present. I have no guarantees, but that’s more interesting anyway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tempus fugit.&lt;/em&gt; Time to start. Let’s see what happens!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on working.</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/thoughts-on-working</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/thoughts-on-working</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This was my 2-inch response to a talk by Richard Hamming called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.cs.virginia.edu/~robins/YouAndYourResearch.html&#34;&gt;“You and Your Research.”&lt;/a&gt; The actual talk is great, and I believe there’s a recording on YouTube. I’ve linked to a transcription in case it a video doesn’t exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think one of the most obvious yet important statements in the entire talk is “you have to neglect things if you intend to get what you want done.” As students, we’re constantly dealing with situations where we just have too much to do. As we grow up, we find that we can’t do everything, and some things must be neglected. I think it’s a difficult choice—to give up, but it’s definitely a necessary choice and one that we must learn to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamming talks about what it takes to produce significant and meaningful results. I agree completely with his claim that an emotional commitment is an essential aspect. I find that when it comes to my work, the best results aren’t only caused by an emotional commitment or sincere dedication. It’s usually an obsession. In order to push yourself to get what you want, you really have to focus fully on the problem, even if that amount of focus requires involves, as Hamming puts it, closed doors.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Frustration.</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/frustration</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/frustration</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/preetamjinka/7046406141/&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/73885ff1382a462b562fbeb97e8e0268/tumblr_inline_mfzgj1Aek61rs73cz.jpg&#34;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like frustration. I like being annoyed by how things work. I like it when I find something wrong about the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Frustration is what drives me. It’s my “engine of creation.” It’s my source of inspiration. Creation isn’t just something that’s done&amp;mdash;it’s a solution to a &lt;em&gt;problem.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy for me to get productive. I just have to get &lt;em&gt;slightly furious.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking up.</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/looking-up</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/looking-up</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;http://www.flickr.com/photos/preetamjinka/7963664676/&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://media.tumblr.com/80deae478469ef4c465103658cd922d8/tumblr_inline_mfzev4AjoF1rs73cz.png&#39; alt=&#39;Stars&#39;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How often do you just look up on a clear night? I’m starting to do it as often as I can. It fascinates me that photons have been traveling for perhaps thousands of years through space to pierce my cornea. It fascinates me that there is so much more to these dots in the sky. There are red supergiants (Betelgeuse), open clusters (Pleides), planets (occasionally), and galaxies (Andromeda). They’re out there. Just look up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s amazing that we’ve been able discover everything so much about the universe just by looking up. Of course, we use telescopes and detectors to help us, but it’s still amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those photons have been traveling for a while. Give them a better destination than the ground.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Journey to Perfection.</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/the-journey-to-perfection</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/the-journey-to-perfection</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#39;http://www.flickr.com/photos/preetamjinka/8137287920/&#39;&gt;&lt;img src=&#39;http://media.tumblr.com/bed1e9476784b6ce68855dd68457d627/tumblr_inline_mfzesjMRqm1rs73cz.jpg&#39; alt=&#39;Hanging by a Silk Thread&#39;/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I start many things. I never finish anything. For some reason, I think of “finishing” as perfecting. I never think of something I create to be perfect. That’s just unrealistic. So here I am with a mountain of works in progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;writing:77596dd56c6d90b9d1dea4ee8e97cfdd&#34;&gt;Writing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think about writing all the time. I’ve been thinking about a certain blog post for months. I think about it when I’m walking to a class, in the bathroom (seriously), or when I’m trying to fall asleep. It’s always in my head, but never out. I have this issue of not taking the time to write down my thoughts. I don’t want to do it because while it makes complete sense for me, it ultimately ends up being incoherent for others. I end up not writing fearing imperfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;guitar:77596dd56c6d90b9d1dea4ee8e97cfdd&#34;&gt;Guitar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really like learning Joe Satriani songs. He’s an amazing guitarist and I aspire to be a guitarist at his level. One of my favorite songs has to be &lt;em&gt;Summer Song.&lt;/em&gt; I distinctly remember the summer of 2009 &amp;ndash; tethering my phone to my laptop and listening to Summer Song on YouTube. It’s an amazing song and I love to play however much I know. It’s been about three years now, and I still haven’t finished learning that song. I keep putting off the rest simply because I want to improve the parts I already know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;good-enough:77596dd56c6d90b9d1dea4ee8e97cfdd&#34;&gt;“Good enough.”&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to stop treating completion as a single target. Work needs iterations. This will sound cliche, but it’s true: perfection is a journey. I need to get into that mindset. This post is &lt;em&gt;good enough.&lt;/em&gt; This blog platform is &lt;em&gt;good enough.&lt;/em&gt; This design is &lt;em&gt;good enough.&lt;/em&gt; I’m not going to start or finish anything with perfection in mind. That would be misframing.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ampless</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/ampless</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Sep 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/ampless</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/4868e27c915ebd069f9ca55ce9cca599/tumblr_inline_mm3t2lduUJ1qz4rgp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Attribution: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.flickr.com/photos/raaphorst/3554002238/&#34;&gt;Marco Raaphorst&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For years I had a beginner’s electric guitar amp. After a while I wasn’t satisfied with the sound that I was getting from it. After looking at (and listening to) products like Native Instrument’s Guitar Rig I decided to transition to a digital rig. Why not just get a better amp? Good amps are expensive! Tube amps sound the best with their warmth and rich distortion, but they need to be cranked to a high volume. I couldn’t have anything too loud in my small bedroom.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Signal Chain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/050f643b9a433bf95726f4f1e09f7453/tumblr_inline_mm3t3t4jJ81qz4rgp.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what people probably care about the most. The iMic is required since the input port on my Macbook doesn’t have microphone-level input. For a while I didn’t use a distortion pedal. I plugged my guitar straight into my computer and tried to introduce the harmonic distortion digitally. That was a whole new challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Distortion pedals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t really have a high-fiedelity setup. Simply put, the amount of noise that is introduced after the iMic is too high to have decent distortion. The audio gets even worse when I apply noise gates and tweak the EQ levels. Eventually, I just grabbed a Satchurator and it’s been providing awesome harmonic distortion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Simulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guitar amps are essentially a preamp, power amp, and the speakers. The power amp drives the speakers—it has little effect on the audio itself. I can forget about simulating that. The preamp and the speakers affect the sound for the most part. You can probably just do some EQ magic for the preamp stuff. It isn’t too complicated. As for the speaker cabinet, it’s also very easy to simulate. All you have to do is apply a speaker cabinet impulse to your source audio.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Convolution Reverb&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The speaker cabinet simulation is &lt;em&gt;the most&lt;/em&gt; important part of the entire system. What I essentially do is simulate my guitar signal going through a speaker cabinet and recorded with a microphone (like an SM57). It’s a really neat application of convolution reverb. We can take some sort of audio signal and modify it so it sounds like it was played somewhere else. If we have the impulse response of a speaker cabinet, we can apply it to any sound and it would sound as if it came out of the speaker cabinet.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Text</title>
      <link>http://misfra.me/its-been-a-long-time-since-johannes-gutenberg</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://misfra.me/its-been-a-long-time-since-johannes-gutenberg</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It’s been a long time since Johannes Gutenberg revolutionized the printing process by developing movable type printing. I’m guessing most people haven’t even seen a printing press in real life—I definitely haven’t. Typesetting back in those days is completely different from what it is now. Typesetters had to physically place movable type into letter cases. Things have changed...well, for most people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/403dd528101ec6f778d536badf3482ec/tumblr_inline_mm3s3fRmum1qz4rgp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Attribution: Willi Heidelbach&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Aardvark Letterpress in Los Angeles is different. It’s a company that still does typesetting the “old” way. I stumbled upon this short film recently, and I think tells an interesting story about this dying industry. I also thought that the filmography was great.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;iframe src=&#34;http://player.vimeo.com/video/33359230?title=0&amp;amp;byline=0&amp;amp;portrait=0&amp;amp;color=ffffff&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;432px&#34; frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Curly quotes&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the most annoying things to find in a document, especially if it is using a serif font, is the lack of “curly quotes.” There’s a reason why straight quotes were made in the first place. Remember typewriters? When they were still made, manufacturers decided to use straight quotes (&#34;) in order to save space and limit the number of characters. It’s a fair decision. The use of straight quotes today, however, is not justified. We’re done with typewriters. Straight quotes are not typographically correct! If you can, use the “curly quotes.” They look much better.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Ligatures&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This definition may not be entirely accurate, but it gets the point across: a ligature is essentially a combination of two or more individual characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/7198242041d445847344871b55c4717f/tumblr_inline_mm3s5jRtM41qz4rgp.png&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;p&gt;It’s incredibly annoying to find characters colliding with each other in documents. I never noticed this issue before, but ever since I found out about it, I can’t stop finding it. Back when movable type was still used, characters never collided. It’s just physically impossible. Ligatures were often used to solve the spacing issue.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/b6416360af2a3f072c4aade55218f66c/tumblr_inline_mm3s4cifWH1qz4rgp.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;div class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Attribution: Daniel Ullrich&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If characters didn’t collide then, why are they colliding now? I don’t understand why typography these days looks worse even though our technology is far superior. Are people really that lazy? It’s even worse when people actually use Times New Roman! Most versions don’t have ligatures! It looks horrible, especially when people sell books using it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;To summarize this section, here is some advice. Use ligatures. Use curly quotes. Don’t use Times New Roman. If you want an alternative, I highly suggest Linux Libertine.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Why Chrome Sucks&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Chrome is my favorite browser. There’s nothing better. It’s awesome, but it also sucks. Here’s why. Chrome has this neat little feature. It’s a CSS rule that is supposed to make everything look amazing. You just add &lt;span style=&#34;font-family: monospace&#34;&gt;text-rendering: optimizeLegibility&lt;/span&gt; to some element and it automatically adds ligatures and improves the kerning! The sad truth is that it murders the kerning, making your text look horrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;http://media.tumblr.com/27a484d68fff2dead385471c6bed78a8/tumblr_inline_mm3s65Pw1Y1qz4rgp.png&#34; alt=&#34;image&#34; /&gt;&lt;h2&gt;LaTeX!&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Some of you may say, “Just use LaTeX! It’s awesome!” Yeah, LaTeX is awesome. I just don’t want to use it. HTML/CSS is ubiquitous. Almost every device has a web browser, and you don’t need to install a bunch of software to work with it. After years of having the web, aren’t we ready to use it for serious typesetting? My answer to that question is, yes—as soon as Chrome gets its act together.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Open Web Documents&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;A friend and I had an idea. The idea was to bring typesetting to the web. What we created was &lt;a href=&#34;http://owdocs.com/&#34;&gt;Open Web Documents&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, we haven’t made too much progress. While the idea is great, the technology just isn’t ready for it. Also, pagination sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>